Guide to the Mark Solomon Papers TAM.741
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mark Solomon Papers
1970-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Solomon, Mark I.
TAM.741
11.5 linear feet in 10 record cartons and 1 oversize flat box
Mark Solomon is a historian and writer who taught History at Simmons College from 1967 to 1997. His papers consist of bulletins, booklets, pamphlets, news articles and magazines pertaining to Solomon's research of and participation in the anti-nuclear war and peace movement during the later years of the Cold War (1979-1991). Topics include nuclear disarmament, military practices in the United States and Soviet Union, human rights, and motions for world peace. Drafts, lectures, outlines and writings by Solomon document the U.S. peace movement and relate to U.S. foreign policy. Correspondence, proposals, conference agendas and presentations document Solomon's affiliation with the U.S. Peace Council and the World Peace Council.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. Materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mark Solomon in 2018; an additional accession was donated by Mark Solomon in December 2018. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2018.083 and 2019.027.
Biographical Note
Mark Solomon is a historian and writer who taught History at Simmons College from 1967 to 1997. Throughout the 1970s and 1980s Solomon was an active participant in the peace movement and served as co-national chairperson of the Communist Party USA's U.S. Peace Council and a U.S. Presidential Committee member of its partner organization, the World Peace Council. Solomon wrote articles for these organizations on the history of 20th-century foreign politics and peace movements in the United States. Solomon also wrote extensively on the United States' military involvement in the Middle East and India. Throughout his professional career Solomon guest lectured and gave presentations at universities and conferences such as Humboldt University of Berlin and the Third European Nuclear Disarmament (END) Convention held in Perugia, Italy in 1984.
Scope and Contents
The Mark Solomon Papers (dated 1974-2000) consist of bulletins, booklets, pamphlets, news articles and magazines documenting Solomon's research of and participation in the United States' anti-nuclear war peace movement during the later years of the Cold War (1979-1991). Topics for these pamphlets and booklets include nuclear disarmament, military practices in the United States and Soviet Union, human rights and motions for world peace. A bulk of the materials are from the 1980s. Drafts, lectures, outlines and essays composed by Solomon pertain to the history of the peace movement in the United States during the 20th century, the arms race between the United States and the Soviet Union in the 1980s and U.S. foreign policy, specifically U.S. relations with the Middle East. Correspondence, proposals, conference agendas and presentations document Solomon's affiliation with the CPUSA's U.S. Peace Council and the World Peace Council.
Peace movements -- United States.; United States -- Foreign relations.; War resistance movements -- United States.; Cold War.; Nuclear disarmament.; Miller, Richard H. (Max Miller)
- News Articles: U.S. Foreign Relations, 1983-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1, 11-13)
- Solomon, Mark: Notebooks, 1973-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
- Muslims of the Soviet East, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bulletin, 1973, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- United States Peace Council, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- New World Review, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Literature on Anti-Nuclear War, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Peace News Bulletin/World Conference for Solidarity Draft, 1979, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- News Bulletins, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
- World Peace Council, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
- International Meeting for Nuclear-Weapon Free Zones, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Insitut fur International Politik and Wirtschaft, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
- Solomon, Mark: Drafts, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
- The Mississippi: Peace Cruise, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Palestine: Politics, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3-4, 7)
- Indonesia Newsletter, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- News Articles: U.S. Foreign Relations, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Literature: U.S. Foreign Relations, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- U.S. Peace Council, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
- World Dialogue Conference, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
- Nordic Peace Conference, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Gabinete de Analises Politicas (M.P.L.A.), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- News Articles, 1981-1988 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
- Soviet Union: Politics, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
- Newsletters: Middle East, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- World Peace Council, 1979-1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- African National Congress, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Communist Party of the Soviet Union, 1971-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- World Peace Council Booklet, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Booklets on German Democratic Republic, 1978, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Labor Booklets, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Booklet on Soviet Union, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- For Life, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- 1987 World Conference Against A&H Bombs (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Five Continent Conference on Peace and Disarmament, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Conferencia Contra La Carrera Armamentista, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Conference Against the Arms Race and for Disarmament, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- World Congress on Disarmament Education, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
- Czechoslovakia Tourist Booklet, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Keine Atomraketen, circa 1982 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Pamphlets on Cold War, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Development and Peace, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- United Nations Booklets, 1978-1985 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
- Literature on Apartheid, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- World Congress of Peace Forces, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Disarmament Booklets, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- United Nations against Apartheid Booklets, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Booklets on German Democratic Republic, 1978, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Disarmament Booklets, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Communist Party of the United States Booklets, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Booklets on Nuclear Disarmament, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 4-6. 14-20)
- Photograph Reproductions of the Army of German Democratic Republic, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Soviet Union Booklets, 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
- Booklets on Peace, 1976, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 11-13)
- Booklets on Socialism, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
- Booklets on German Democratic Republic, undated (Box 5, Folder 1, 4-5)
- New World Review, 1981, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Soviet Union Booklets, 1974-1981 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Booklets on Peace, 1979-1986 (Box 5, Folder 6-8, 10-13, 15-16)
- World Marxist Review, 1966-1969 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Book on Nuclear War, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- World Peace Council, 1987-1990 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
- Euromissiles, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Socialism, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Magazines on Nuclear Warfare, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Century and Peace, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 8, 11)
- Blatter fur deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
- Booklets on Military, 1979-1981 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Development and Peace, 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 13-16)
- Booklets on German Democratic Republic, 1983-1989 (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
- Booklets on World Peace, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Century and Peace, 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Palestine: United Nations, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
- World Peace Council Booklets, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 4, 10, 12)
- Booklets by L.I. Brezhnev, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- World Congress of Peace Forces Booklets, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Booklets on Soviet Union, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 7-8, 13-16)
- United States: Foreign Relations, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- World Congress of Peace Forces Booklets, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- The Burden of the Berrigans, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Booklets on Peace, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- World Parliament of the Peoples for Peace, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Middle East, 1984-1988 (Box 8, Folder 1-2, 19)
- SALT - Consolidated File, 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 3-5)
- Arms Race: Assorted Clippings/Materials, 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- "Soviet Threat" - Materials, 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- World Peace Council, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Detente and Arms Race, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- American Peace Movement and the Middle East, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Indian Ocean Bases Materials, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- "Development and Disarmament: The Importance of International Cooperation", circa 1975 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Garcia, Diego, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- U.S. Committee for German Democratic Republic, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- India -- Patna Conference/Patna Address, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- India, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Indian Ocean Bases, circa 1975 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- International Contacts, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- National Council of Soviet-American Friendship, Inc., 1976 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- New World Review, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Women Strike for Peace, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Women's International League, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Arvin S. Quist, E.U. Franck, H.R. Jolley, and W.L. Marshall, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 24)
- Globalization and Empire, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Korean War Racial Discrimination, circa 2000 (Box 8, Folder 26)
- Globalization, Peace, Economic Security, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 27)
- Germany Cold War: Party of Democratic Socialism - German Democratic Republic, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Middle East: Issues and Policies, 1975-1981 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- European Nuclear Disarmament (END) Convention in Perugia, Italy, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
- Peace Movement: History Poject, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Middle East and Peace Movement, 1974-1976 (Box 9, Folder 6-8)
- Transnational Corporations, 1973-1975 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Peace Movement: Organization Materials, 1978-1982 (Box 9, Folder 10-11)
- Solomon, Mark: Manuscripts, Speeches, Addresses, 1977-1983 (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
- Africa-Latin America, 1979-1987 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Middle East: Peace Organizations and Proposals, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- "Star Wars", 1984 (Box 9, Folder 16-17)
- Disarmament/Common Security, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Japanese Military Photo Reproductions (in Japanese), 1982 (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
- Peace Multinationals, Neocolonialism, 1974-1991 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Peace Movement 1980s, 1984-1988 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
- Assorted Articles and Talks, 1981-2018 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- World Peace Council and European Contacts, 1977-2005 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
- Multinationals, Racism, Peace, 1973-2017 (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
- Talks and Papers, 1974-1992 (Box 11, Folder 9-10)
- Talks, 1974-2014 (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Development and Disarmament, June -July 1973, 1973-1975 (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Talks and Articles, 1972-2009 (Box 11, Folder 13-14)
- Mid-East Materials, 1973-74, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 15)
- BPC and May 7-8 Delegation, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Vietnam - 1975, 1974-1975 (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Miller, Max, 1970-1976 (Box 11, Folder 18)
- Talks and Notes, 2009-2017 (Box 11, Folder 19)